<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- For standalone validation, uncomment the following DOCTYPE declaration. -->
<!--
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
-->
<article id="frrelnotes">
  <articleinfo>
    <title><application>FlameRobin</application> 0.2.5 ALPHA Release
    Notes</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Nando</firstname>

      <surname>Dessena</surname>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="frrelnotes-alphatest">
    <title>About the ALPHA test program</title>

    <para>Welcome to the FlameRobin Alpha test! We thank you for evaluating
    this software and encourage you to send comments, bug reports and feature
    requests back to us so we can make a better product. We remind you that
    this is Alpha quality software so you shouldn't expect it to work
    flawlessly (although we use it for daily work already). The main purpose
    of this very early release is finding bugs and tune the user interface,
    for which we need feedback from the prospect users.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-what-fr-is">
    <title>What FlameRobin is</title>

    <para>FlameRobin is a GUI administration and data manipulation tool for
    Firebird servers and databases. It is designed to be small, simple and
    cross-platform, yet offer all the basic features needed to administer
    Firebird servers and create/maintain databases. FlameRobin is Open Source
    software and binaries are currently available for Windows, several
    GNU/Linux flavours and MacOS X. Ports to other platforms are possible,
    subject to the availability of maintainers for those platforms.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-what-fr-is-not">
    <title>What FlameRobin is NOT</title>

    <para>Currently FlameRobin is not a full-featured administration tool, as
    there are plenty available for Firebird from several different parties.
    Our first goal with FlameRobin is to provide people not used to the
    command line with a GUI tool to get started with Firebird. Our longer-term
    goal is to develop a richer tool mainly for the Linux market; while there
    are several rich and mature GUI tools under Windows, some of them
    available for free or for a modest price, there isn't any for Linux.
    Another goal for the "lite" edition of FlameRobin is to be bundled with
    the Firebird server to serve as a starting kit for new users - this is
    subject to approval by the Firebird Project, which may have alternative
    tools at hand.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-who-we-are">
    <title>Who we are</title>

    <para>The home page of the FlameRobin project is located at <ulink
    url="http://www.flamerobin.org">http://www.flamerobin.org</ulink>. The
    project itself is hosted on <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/flamerobin">SourceForge</ulink>.
    Please use our mailing list (flamerobin-devel) to contact the developers.
    Details and archives available <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=124340">here</ulink>. You are
    also encouraged to use our <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=124340&amp;atid=699234">bugs</ulink>
    and <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=124340&amp;atid=699237">feature
    requests</ulink> trackers to report back to us the results of your alpha
    testing. If you are a developer interested in joining the FlameRobin
    project, let us know. We always welcomelooking for contributors.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-license">
    <title>License</title>

    <para>FlameRobin is released under the Initial Developer's Public License.
    You can find the complete license text in the file license.html, or <ulink
    url="http://www.flamerobin.org/license.html">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-changes">
    <title>What's new?</title>

    <para>Please refer to changes.txt for a detailed history of all the
    changes since the previous alpha release.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>If you want to build FlameRobin from sources, please find
    instructions on our web site or CVS. In this section we talk about
    installing the pre-built version of FlameRobin under all currently
    supported platforms.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Windows (Win32)</title>

      <para>To install FlameRobin under Windows you need to have the Firebird
      client (gds32.dll for Firebird 1.0, fbclient.dll for Firebird 1.5 and
      up) installed and available, then just run the automatic installer of
      FlameRobin which will copy all required files in a directory of your
      choice and optionally create desktop and start menu shortcuts. If you
      have installed a previous alpha version of FlameRobin, it is recommended
      that you remove it before installing this version. You might be able to
      keep your servers.xml and config.ini files, but at this early stage of
      development we cannot guarantee that.</para>

      <para>Here are the files used by FlameRobin to store configuration
      information:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>servers.xml is the list of Firebird servers and databases you
          work with; FlameRobin will create it (and automatically add the
          "localhost" server) when you run it for the first time; then you can
          register new servers and databases (see documentation).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>config.ini stores FlameRobin's configuration information, like
          the position and size of the main program window. You don't need to
          edit it by hand except when wanting to turn on/off some special
          features (see documentation).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>The name, structure and location of these files is going to
        change in a future release, certainly before release 1.0.</para>
      </note>

      <para>If you need to uninstall FlameRobin you can do so from the start
      menu icon (unless you told the installation program not to create one)
      or from the Control Panel.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Linux</title>

      <para>For the time being, unpacking the supplied archive into a
      directory of your choice will do.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MacOS X</title>

      <para>N/A.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-getting-started">
    <title>Getting started</title>

    <para>Upon first startup, FlameRobin will present a "Firebird Servers"
    tree containing only the local server (localhost), and will invite you to
    create new servers and databases as required. Here is a brief how-to for
    getting started with FlameRobin.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Adding a server</title>

      <para>You can add a server by righ-clicking in "Firebird Servers" and
      choosing "Register server...". You will have to specify the host name
      and the TCP port number (default 3050) on which it listens. Once you
      have added a server, you can register databases under its node.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding an existing database</title>

      <para>To access an existing database from FlameRobin you have to
      register it. Registration will make FlameRobin remember the database
      connection properties so you don't have to re-enter them every time.
      Locate the correct server in the tree, right click it and choose
      "Register existing database...". You will have to enter the database
      path (or alias name), the user name and password (note: the password is
      stored as plain text in servers.xml. For security reasons, we recommend
      you to NOT specify it in this dialog: FlameRobin will then prompt you
      for the password each time you connect to the database). You can also
      optionally specify a connection charset and role.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating a new database</title>

      <para>To create a new, empty database, locate the desired server in the
      tree, right click it and choose "Create new database...". You will then
      need to input the database file or alias name, the user name and
      password for the owner of the new database (use SYSDBA as the user name
      and masterkey if you don't know what to put in these fields), the
      character set, the role, the page size (the default value of 4096 is
      just fine) and the SQL dialect (leave it set at 3 if you don't know what
      a SQL dialect is). The new database will be created and registered
      (which means it is available in FlameRobin).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Connecting to a registered database</title>

      <para>Just double click on the database name in the tree, or right click
      it and choose "Connect". Choose "Disconnect" to close the connection to
      the database.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Browsing metadata</title>

      <para>Upon connection, the sub-tree under the database name is populated
      with a description of the database structure (metadata). Browse the tree
      to explore the metadata.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Editing objects</title>

      <para>You can view and/or change the properties of every object you see
      in the tree by choosing the "Properties..." option. Please note that
      currently not all object types are supported. Trying to show the
      property page for an object of an unsupported type will result in a
      blank page. The property page is a HTML window with a summary of the
      object's properties and links which open other pages or specific
      editors. Some of the options are not yet available, but you can f. ex.
      edit almost all aspects of the most common objects (tables, views,
      stored procedures, and so on). Please have a look at changes.txt to see
      what's new.<note>
          <para>Although we try to test the features as much as we can, this
          is ALPHA software and you should only use it to work on backup
          copies of your databases, or perform backup copies before using
          FlameRobin on them. Having said that, we have to add that many of us
          use FlameRobin in their everyday Firebird development without a
          problem.</para>
        </note></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Browsing data</title>

      <para>After connecting to a database, locate a table, view or selectable
      stored procedure of your interest in the tree and right-click it.
      Choosing either "Select ... from ..." option will open the SQL editor
      with the table/view data shown in the lower grid. In the case of
      selectable stored procedures with parameters, just the select statement
      appears in the SQL editor, so you should fill the parameter values (if
      you have any) and click the Execute button to see the data.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running SQL statements and scripts</title>

      <para>Of course you can use the SQL editor window to execute arbitrary
      SQL statements. You can open a SQL editor window by right clicking on a
      database node and choosing "Run a query". The SQL editor tool offers
      script execution capabilities (including SET TERM support), load/save
      buttons, auto-completion and call-tip features, commit/rollback, some
      execution statistics (including but not limited to the query PLAN), and
      a data export tool: to activate it, right click on the data grid. The
      data export tool is currently able to copy the data to the clipboard,
      generate SQL INSERT statements or export the data to a HTML file. All
      options work on the whole grid contents or just the selected parts. You
      can also multiple-select several different grid "islands" and have the
      tool export them.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Advanced tools</title>

      <para>You can perform a database backup by right clicking on a database
      and choosing "Backup database...". Choose "Restore database..." to
      restore a backup file over the current database (you will have to
      disconnect first). Note: it is usually considered bad practice to
      restore a backup file over an existing database. Future versions of
      FlameRobin will probably provide a way to restore under a different file
      name. For the time being, you can do that by registering a new (non
      existing) database in FlameRobin and restore over it. The Backup and
      Restore features work in background, so you are allowed to continue
      working with FlameRobin while they proceed.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="frrelnotes-configuration">
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <para>This section documents the options you can set to tune FlameRobin's
    behaviour to your liking. You can set the options by means of the
    Preferences dialog, which is invoked through the "Preferences..." menu
    command in the local menu of the tree's root node. The Preferences are
    organized in categories; here is a description of each category. Please
    read the tooltip that appears when you move the mouse cursor over each
    option to know more about it.</para>

    <section>
      <title>General</title>

      <para>Here you can find options to tune the visual appearance and
      behaviour of FlameRobin. You can choose whether FlameRobin will remember
      the size and position of opened windows between sessions or not, whether
      FlameRobin will ask for quit confirmation or not, and other such
      things.</para>

      <para>Set this option to 1 to enable storing size and position of each
      window (frame) on closing. Set it to 0 to disable the feature.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The object properties frame's storage option can be further
        customized, see MetadataFrameStorageGranularity.</para>
      </note>

      <section>
        <title>Center dialogs on their parent window</title>

        <para>Set this option to always have dialogs displayed at the center
        of their parent window. Otherwise dialogs are displayed at a
        system-defined position.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Remember window positions and sizes</title>

        <para>If you enable this option, FlameRobin will remember the position
        and size of each window you open and will open the same window at the
        same position and with the same time the next time. You can also
        choose the granularity of this option for property pages and
        backup/restore dialogs:</para>

        <para><itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Choose "Same settings for all objects" to store a single
              set of values; this means that whenever an Object Properties
              dialog is opened it will have the position and size of the last
              Object Properties dialog used.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Select "Same settings for all objects of same type" to
              store a set of values for each object type. This means that a
              Table Properties dialog will have different settings than a
              Trigger Properties dialog, but two Table Properties dialog will
              share the same set of values.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The third option, "Separate settings for individual
              objects", will make it so that every object's property page will
              have a set of options of its own. This mode is the most
              flexible, but consumes more disk space and memory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Confirm quit</title>

        <para>Set this option to have FlameRobin ask you for quit
        confirmation.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Main Tree View</title>

      <para>Here you can tune the appearance and behaviour of FlameRobin's
      metadata navigation tool, the main tree.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Order server entries alphabetically</title>

        <para>Set this option to have your servers displayed in alphabetical
        order, otherwise they are displayed in the order they appear in
        servers.xml.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Order database entries alphabetically</title>

        <para>Set this option to have your databases displayed in alphabetical
        order, otherwise they are displayed in the order they appear in
        servers.xml.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>When a column has a user-defined domain</title>

        <para>In this case you can choose to see only the domain, only the
        datatype or both domain and datatype in the tree item's
        caption.</para>

        <note>
          <para>This option only applies when columns are displayed in the
          tree (see the folowwing option).</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Show columns and parameters in tree</title>

        <para>Enable this option to have table/view columns and procedure
        parameters displayed as tree nodes; otherwise, the tree stops at the
        table/view or procedure level. In case you choose to have columns and
        parameters displayed as tree nodes, you can also indicate whether you
        wish that a double click on a table/view or procedure node opens the
        relevant property page or expands the subtree.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>SQL Editor</title>

      <para>Use these options to customize the behaviour of the SQL Editor,
      which is used in FlameRobin to execute any kind of system-generated or
      user-supplied query.</para>

      <section>
        <title>When text is selected in editor</title>

        <para>This options turns on and off a useful feature of the SQL
        Editor: you can type in or paste several SQL statements and execute
        just one of them by selecting it before hitting the Execute button. If
        for some reason you'd like to always execute the content of the whole
        editor buffer, then disable this option.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Treat selected text as a single statement</title>

          <para>If you only ever select a single statement at a time, then you
          can save FlameRobin's parser some work by enabling this option. When
          this option is disabled, FlameRobin will parse the selected text
          before executing it, break it into several statements if necessary
          and send them to Firebird one at a time; this is necessary since
          Firebird does not support executing more than one statement (i.e. a
          script) at a time.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Clear the messages when executing new statements</title>

          <para>The SQL Editor has a message pane that shows information about
          each executed statement. By default this pane is never cleared
          automatically. Set this option to have FlameRobin clear it before
          executing a statement.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Enable call-tips for procedures and functions</title>

          <para>When this option is enabled, then each time you type an open
          round bracket after a stored procedure or UDF name in the SQL
          Editor, a floating tooltip (called a call-tip) will appear reminding
          you what the input parameters of the stored procedure or UDF
          are.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>SQL Code Completion</title>

          <para>This page contains options to customize FlameRobin's code
          completion feature.</para>

          <section>
            <title>Enable automatic invocation of completion list</title>

            <para>This is the general switch to turn automatic code completion
            in the SQL Editor on or off. Disable it if you don't like code
            completion windows that pop up while you write SQL code. If you
            keep it enabled, then you can set a certain number of characters
            you'll have to type before code completion kicks in (default 5),
            and choose to disable code completion when a call-tip is
            displayed.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Manually invoke auto-complete list on</title>

            <para>Code completion may also be invoked manually. Here you
            select how (Ctrl+Space or Tab key).</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Allow auto-completion with Enter</title>

            <para>Set this option to have the currently selected item in the
            code completion window copied to the text buffer when you hit
            Enter.</para>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Data Grid</title>

      <para>When you issue a SQL SELECT statement in the SQL Editor, then the
      Data Grid comes into play to show the results. Here you customize its
      appearance and behaviour.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Date format</title>

        <para>Choose the format you'd like for showing date and timestamp
        values in the grid.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Time format</title>

        <para>Choose the format you'd like for showing time and timestamp
        values in the grid.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Grid header font</title>

        <para>Choose a character font for the grid header (the column
        names).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Grid cell font</title>

        <para>Choose a character font for the grid cells (the data).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Re-format float and double precision numbers</title>

        <para>If unchecked, decimal numbers are displayed as returned from
        server; otherwise, they are formatted according to the specified
        number of decimal digits.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Maximize data grid after execution of SELECT statement</title>

        <para>Here you can turn off an useful feature that will enlarge the
        data grid to the maximum available size when a SQL SELECT statement
        returns more than a specified number of rows.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Logging</title>

      <para>The SQL Editor can log all executed statements to a text file
      (and, in a future release, to a database table). Here you set the
      options to tune this feature.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Log DML statements</title>

        <para>When logging is enabled, by default only DDL (data definition)
        statements are logged. Turn this option on to enable logging of DML
        (data manipulation) statements as well.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Enable logging to file</title>

          <para>Here you choose whether you want to log statements or not,
          select the log file name(s), and choose if you want to output for
          each statement also a comment with the version of FlameRobin,
          database and user name, and execution date and time.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>